<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of St. Gregorie his dialogues: in which the great St. Gregory is proved the author of that work.</title>
            <author>Mumford, J. (James), 1606-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3071A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222057</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1783:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of St. Gregorie his dialogues: in which the great St. Gregory is proved the author of that work.</title>
                  <author>Mumford, J. (James), 1606-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, 17-19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Crooke, at the Ship in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>By James Mumford.</note>
                  <note>Leaf A2 is incorrectly signed A3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gregory --  I, --  Pope, ca. 540-604 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Saints, Italian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF St. Gregorie HIS DIALOGUES: IN WHICH The Great St. Gregory is proved The Author of that Work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Crooke,</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37771:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37771:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Vindication of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> his <hi>Dialogues,</hi> in which the <hi>Great St. Gregory</hi> is proved the Author of that Work.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> CErtain modern writers have not long ſince affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Opinion, avouching ſouls to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverable from Purgatory before the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was an Opinion which St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great brought into the Church, by certain petty ſtories. That he was the Father of this Opinion, and the leader unto it, and that cleerly this Opinion began about his times. Yet as clear as they reported this to be, now of late, this Clarity is clearly acknowledged by them to be a flat falſity, and that in two ſeveral books: whence <hi>upon fuller Conſideration,</hi> they profeſs themſelves to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Authority of venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> attributing the book of Dialogues to St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective; yea they openly profeſs this book to be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy St. <hi>Gregory.</hi> Why ſo? becauſe (ſay they) nothing like <hi>ſuch winter tales,</hi> as are told in that book, can be found in his moſt worthy and learned works. By this they being enforced to ſeek out another Author; upon whom they might Father theſe Dialogues, they fall into ſo great a weakneſs, as to aſcribe this work to that Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> to whom Pope <hi>Zacharias</hi> did ſucceed, whom they ſay to have been by the Grecians called <hi>Gregorius Dialogus,</hi> who lived about the midſt of the eight age, that is to St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, a <hi>Syrian.</hi> All this they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm by the the authority of <hi>Photius,</hi> a Man who could not (as they conceive) be well ignorant thereof, being ſo learned a perſon, eſpecially in books and Authors.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37771:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> By this invention they imagine themſelves to make our doctrine a hundred years later, and to make it firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in an Age of the leaſt cultivated, ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For our parts we are no wayes ambitious to have ſo worthy a Father, as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, to be Father to our Opinion. For we eſteem our doctrine of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverableneſs of ſouls before the laſt day, to have had no later beginning, then the doctrine of Purgatory it ſelf, which was delivered (as part of the firſt faith) by the Teachers of that faith: neither will they ever be able to ſhew any other Origin of it, which is an evident proof of its verity. But becauſe St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great is ſo clear an Aſſertor of this verity in his Dialogues, and a Man ſo far from introducing any novelty into the Church; or from believing any novelty to be confirmed by miracle (as he believes this verity to be) his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is not to be wreſted from us, by ſo groundleſs a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of his Dialogues, which, upon this <hi>their fuller con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> they moſt inconſiderately affirm not to be his work, but to have been written by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third. An opinion ſo full of moſt enormious and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abſurdities, and that in ſo great number, that their adhering to it upon <hi>fuller conſideration,</hi> ſhews how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, their authority ought to be eſteemed, even when this <hi>fuller Conſideration</hi> is uſed by them. Againſt this Opinion we argue thus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Firſt, that holy and learned St. <hi>Ildefonſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo</hi> (who dyed Anno. 667.) in his book <hi>de viris illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> C. 1. (whoſe Original manuſcript is ſtill kept in the <hi>Vatican</hi> library, as <hi>Baronius</hi> certifies, Anno. 604.) writeth thus of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great. <hi>He did ſet forth four books compriſed in one Volume, concerning the lives of the Italian Fathers, which he would have called by the name of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues. In which books how great ſecrets of Diviniy lye hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and what wonderfull Documents, of the love of our Heavenly Countrey, any carefull Reader may eaſily perceive.</hi> Do you not ſee here theſe books known and highly eſteemed in the Church before either <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37771:3"/> yea or <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, was of age to write or read a book? Again, do you not ſee how, according to the Judgment of this great Father, that <hi>Reader</hi> of theſe Dialogues is no <hi>carefull Reader,</hi> who doth not eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>great ſecrets of Divinity hidden in this book of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues?</hi> Which our Adverſaries, <hi>upon their fuller conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> think <hi>unworthy of St. Gregory,</hi> and <hi>like to Winter Tales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Secondly, St. <hi>Julian</hi> Biſhop alſo of <hi>Toledo,</hi> (who flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, Anno. 688) citeth theſe Dialogues in his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnosticon L.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 7. <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 19. <hi>C.</hi> 24. An evident proof that they were made before either of the other two <hi>Gregories</hi> (eſpecially <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third) were known in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thirdly, our Adverſaries do indeed take notice that <hi>Bede</hi> cites theſe Dialogues, and aſcribes them to our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>Gregory.</hi> But they did not conſider, in their fuller conſideration, where, and when <hi>Bede</hi> did ſay what he ſaid. Where ſaid he this? In his Hiſtory of <hi>England.</hi> When did he write that Hiſtory? He himſelf, in the end of this Hiſtory, tells us, that he did end it, <hi>Anno.</hi> 731. So that <hi>Bede</hi> did write what he writ concerning theſe Dialogues, that very year in which Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond dyed, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third was made Pope. How ſurely then might <hi>Bede</hi> know that theſe Dialogues, (out of which he tranſcribed the complaint of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> concerning the loſs of his former retirement, by being advanced to the Popedom) were not made by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third, who as then was not made Pope, neither could ſo freſh a work of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Second, which muſt have been made in <hi>Bedes</hi> own floriſhing Age (for <hi>Bede</hi> was 59. years old when he ended his Hiſtory, as <hi>Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> proves Anno. 731) be ſo much miſtaken, by ſuch a Man as <hi>Bede</hi> was, for a work ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t forth above a hundred years before.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Fourthly, <hi>Joannes Diaconus,</hi> who moſt accurately did write the Life of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, is an Author, both more ancient, and of more Credit, then <hi>Photius,</hi> and a Man particularly verſed in the works of St. <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37771:4"/> the great. And yet he writeth thus, L. 4. <hi>Theſe books</hi> (of <hi>St. Gregory</hi> the great his Dialogues) <hi>Zacharias Biſhop of the holy Roman Church, almoſt a hundred and ſeventy five years after, tranſlated into Greek.</hi> Theſe words <hi>Baronius</hi> in his notes upon the Martyr: Dec. 23. having cited, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on thus. <hi>How much the Grecians esteemed theſe books, you may hence understand, that when they cite Gregory, they call him by the very name of Dialogus,</hi> that is the Dialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſt. And again in his Annals (Anno. 726.) ſpeaking of an Epiſtle of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Second (<hi>The Second</hi> I ſay, and not <hi>the Third</hi>) he ſaith, <hi>That Epiſtle falſely bears the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Gregorius Dialogus, an errour with which we find many Grecians, and ſome Latines to have been deceived, whilst this Gregory</hi> (the Second) <hi>is called Dialogus, which ſurname, it is manifeſt out of Greek and Latine Authors, to be appropriated by the Grecians to Gregory the great, ever ſince Zacharias the Pope did tranſlate his Dialogues into Greek, ſo to diſtinguiſh him from the three other Gregories, Thauma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgus, Nazienzen and Nyſſen.</hi> Therefore our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are much miſtaken, who, in their fuller conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will have <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third to have been called <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus.</hi> But leaſt retiring themſelves to conſider more fully, they ſhould Father theſe Dialogues upon <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond (who dyed Anno. 731.) I deſire them to ponder how demonſtratively the contrary is proved, by the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments already brought. And yet more demonſtratively, (if it may) the ſame is farther proved by ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as I am now going to produce out of the book of Dialogues it ſelf, which, if they had peruſed in their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler conſideration (as any conſiderate writers would have done) they would have been aſhamed of ſo unexcuſable an ignorance, as apparently is committed in averring theſe Dialogues to have been written by <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and much more, in aſcribing them to <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third, made Pope. Anno 731. I pray note this year and then you will ſoon note the groſneſs of this abſurdity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Fifthly then, the books of Dialogues need only an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Reader, to make it evident that <hi>Gregory</hi> the great was, and that neither <hi>Gregory</hi> the Second, or Third,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37771:4"/> could be the Author of that book. In his Preface to his ſecond book he writes thus. <hi>What I intend to recount of St. Bennet</hi> (who dyed Anno. 543.) <hi>I had by Relation of four of his diſciples. Of Constantius, who was next Abbat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him; of Valentinianus; of Simplicius; of Honoratus, who now is Abbat.</hi> Theſe Men were diſciples to <hi>St. Bennet</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 200. years before <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third was Pope. How then could he have what he related from their mouths? Or how could any of them be living in his time?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Again he ſaith, L. 3. C. 4. <hi>now I will relate ſuch miracles as happened in my own dayes.</hi> Then C. 11. He relates, how <hi>Cerbonius</hi> was <hi>brought forth and caste to a Bear, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, in the ſight of King Totilas himſelf,</hi> and his whole army, the bear doing reverence to the Saint. <hi>Many of them who were preſent and ſaw it, be yet living.</hi> Now it is evident that <hi>Totilas</hi> dyed Anno. 553. ſo that you muſt make theſe <hi>many eye witneſſes</hi> to have lived <hi>a hundred and fourſcore years</hi> after they did ſee this wonder, that ſo they might be yet <hi>living</hi> in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third. And C. 12. <hi>A certain old Priest</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who yet liveth, was preſent, when Fulgentius Biſhop of Otricoli was taken by Totilas,</hi> ſee here the ſame argument again. And it recurs again in the next Chapter, where it is ſaid. <hi>Floridus told me a notable miracle of Herculanus, who did bring him up, and in whoſe time Totilas beſieged Perugia for ſeven years together.</hi> And yet again, in the fourteenth Chapter it is made further evident, that the Author of the Dialogues was a neer borderer upon the day of <hi>Toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las.</hi> For there he ſaith, <hi>at ſuch time as the Goths (by Toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) firſt invaded Italy, there was a holy Man, Iſaac, well known to the holy Virgin Gorgonia, who now dwelleth in this City.</hi> And preſently after he ſaith. <hi>This holy man Iſaac, was not born in Italy, and therefore I will only ſpeak of ſuch miracles as he did here in our Countrey.</hi> Do not theſe words tell you that the Countrey of the Author of the Dialogues, was <hi>Italy,</hi> and not <hi>Syria?</hi> But what can demonſtrate more clearly, that the Great St. <hi>Gregory</hi> was Author of theſe Dialogues, then what followeth Chap. 16. <hi>There</hi> was (ſaith he) <hi>a Reverend man in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37771:5"/> called</hi> Marcius, <hi>whom many of our acquaintance knew very well, and many things concerning him I have heard from the mouth of Pope</hi> Pelagius <hi>my Predeceſſor.</hi> Now whoſe Predeceſſor was Pope <hi>Pelagius?</hi> All the World knows St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great did ſucceed him immediately. As alſo that no Pope called <hi>Pelagius</hi> lived neerer to <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, then this foreſaid <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſecond, who died <hi>Anno</hi> 590. How then could either <hi>Gregory</hi> the third or ſecond <hi>Hear many things from the mouth of Pope</hi> Pelagius, who ceaſed both to ſpeak, and to live a whole age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either of them were <hi>born?</hi> Yet again C. 19. <hi>We had in our dayes one other miracle. For not long ſince,</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Tribune <hi>told me, that when the Earle</hi> Pronulphus <hi>was there, and himſelf alſo with</hi> Antharicus <hi>the King, almoſt five years ſince, when the River of</hi> Tiber <hi>became ſo great, that it ran over the walls of Rome.</hi> Behold here two manifeſt proofes that the Author of the Dialogues did write the ſaid books <hi>five years</hi> after the <hi>Inundation</hi> which happened <hi>Anno</hi> 589. as you may ſee in <hi>Baronius.</hi> At what time <hi>Antharith</hi> was King of the <hi>Longobards,</hi> ſo created by them <hi>Anno</hi> 585 Though he called himſelf <hi>Flavius,</hi> as the ſame <hi>Baronius</hi> in that year teſtifyes. All this demonſtrates our opinion and ſhames the contrary. It followeth in the Chap. 31. that which the Roman Breviary did tranſcribe out of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great concerning St. <hi>Hermenigild,</hi> in which be theſe words, St. <hi>Hermenigild was converted by</hi> Leander <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Sevil, <hi>a man long ſince joyned to me in familiarity and friendſhip.</hi> This <hi>Leander,</hi> with whom St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great was ſo intirely acquainted, is the ſame to whom he writes, L. 1. Epiſt. 41. L. 4. Epiſt. 46. L. 7. Epiſt. 125. And our Adverſaries (to verifie thoſe words in <hi>Gregory</hi> the third) muſt make him acquainted with one, who dyed above a hundred years before he was born. Again Chap. 33. it is ſaid, <hi>in the time of</hi> Juſtinian <hi>the Emperour,</hi> the King of the <hi>Wandals</hi> commanded the tongues of certain Biſhops to be pulled out by the roots for preaching againſt the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſy, yet they did as perfectly afterwards ſpeak in defence of the true religion, as before. <hi>And at ſuch time as I my ſelf was ſent to Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37771:5"/> unto the Emperor about the affairs of the Church, I found there a Biſhop of good years, who told me that he ſaw them himſelf, ſpeak without tongues.</hi> Now it is notorius, that St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great was ſent about the affairs of the Church to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and that <hi>Juſtinian</hi> began to riegn <hi>Anno</hi> 587. that is, full two hundred years before <hi>Gregory</hi> the third was Pope. How then could <hi>Gregory</hi> the third ſpeak with any Biſhop, who had ſeen thoſe worthy Biſhops, whoſe tongues had been pulled out <hi>in the dayes of</hi> Juſtinian.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Again the Author of the Dialogues in his fourth book, not only frequently cites his own Homiles (which are known to be the Homilies of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, of which ſee here by and by N. 18.) but C. 16. he ſaith, <hi>I will here repeat that which I remember alſo to have ſpoke in my Homilies concerning my Aunt</hi> Tarſilla. <hi>To this Woman</hi> Felix <hi>my Grandfather, ſometimes Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>appeared in viſion.</hi> Who is ſo blind, as not to ſee that theſe words cannot be ſpoken by <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, who had no ſuch <hi>Italian</hi> kindred, for he was a <hi>Syrian?</hi> But they are clearly ſpoken by the great St. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſo well known by his Homilies, and by his Aunt, and by his Grandfather. And C. 26. He thus deſcribes the year in which he did write theſe Dialogues, <hi>Likewiſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in that mortality which three years ſince lamentably afflicted this town.</hi> It is notorius by Hiſtory, that this great plague raged in <hi>Rome</hi> the firſt year of his Popedom, of which ſee <hi>Baronius, Anno</hi> 590. who well proves from hence that theſe Dialogues were written <hi>Anno.</hi> 593. ſee him in that year. Moreover C. 30. The writer of theſe Dialogues ſpeak thus, <hi>Julian who dyed almost ſeven years ſince, told me this Story. In the time of King Theodoricus</hi> (quoth he) <hi>my Wives father being then in Sicily, Theodoricus</hi> began to reign <hi>Anno</hi> 493. How could <hi>Gregory</hi> the third (made Pope <hi>Anno</hi> 731.) ſpeak theſe words? Lord! where is theſe mens <hi>fuller conſideration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The Church in her Breviary is, a moſt exact deliverer ſo hiſtorical Verity, and not a follower of ſuch as deliver Winter tales. This Church, upon the feaſt of St. <hi>Hemeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gildus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37771:6"/> April</hi> 13. taketh the leſſons of the ſecond Nocturne out of theſe Dialogues of St. <hi>Gregory.</hi> And upon the feaſt of St. <hi>John Pope and Martyr, May</hi> the 27. the ſame Church recounts out of theſe Dialogues of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> one of theſe ſtories (which they are pleaſed to Nickname Winter tales concerning a holy Eremite, who did ſee the ſoul of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricus</hi> caſt down into the fire of <hi>Sipara</hi> the ſame day &amp; hower upon which he dyed, of which ſee L. 4. C. 30.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> the ſame Church is known to have uſed moſt accurate diligence in the Hiſtory of her Roman Maryro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loge, which ſhe appoints to be read dayly in the Quire at the Prime, as part of the divine office, in which it were moſt groſſe to follow the Relaters of Winter tales: yet in a ſhort time, I found above twenty ſeveral places in that Martyrologe, in which St. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his Dialogues is cited in confirmation of what is here related, of which I ſhall ſpeak more herafter. N. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> to all theſe convincing proofs I add the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great in that undoubted work of his epiſtles. Where he tells us clearly that he did write the book of Dialogues, and upon what occaſion. Thus then he writeth <hi>Epist.</hi> 50. L. 2. <hi>Regist. Indict.</hi> 11. C. 89. To <hi>Maxmianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Syracuſa. My Brethren who live familiarly with me do inforce me by all means briefly to commit to writing ſome miracles of thoſe fathers which we have heard done in</hi> Italy, <hi>for effecting whereof I stand in great need of your charitable aſſistance, to wit, that you would ſignifie to me ſuch things, as came to your memorie, or it hath been your chance to know, for I remember well, You told me ſome things concerning</hi> Abbot, Annoſus, <hi>who lived neer</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtaſius, &amp;c. Now it appears by his firſt book of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues C. 7. that this <hi>Maximianus</hi> did write back unto him what he there relates of <hi>Abbot, Annoſus.</hi> And by all this, any man may ſee how inconſiderately, in their fuller conſideration, they have proceeded, who, never opening their eyes to any of theſe ſo apparent verities, did moſt unadviſedly deny theſe Dialogues to be written by the great St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and fathered them upon <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the the third. But novv they have heard our argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37771:6"/> which are ſo wholly unanſwerable, let us hear their very weak proofes of the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <hi>Firſt, they object</hi> the Authority of <hi>Photius</hi> (aſcribing theſe books to <hi>Gregory the Third</hi>) a Man ſo learned in books and Authors, that he cannot be conceived igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the truth. I anſwer, that <hi>this Photius</hi> was a Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and nothing well skilled in ſacred, and Latin Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. Hear what <hi>Nicetas</hi> writeth in his Life, in which he ſaith, that he was eminent indeed in ſecular ſciences, being ſecretary to the Emperour <hi>Bardas.</hi> But <hi>wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of all ſacred literature.</hi> And no wonder. For, as he tells us, That <hi>of a Lay man, he, in ſpace of ſix dayes, was transformed into a Patriarch of Conſtantinople.</hi> From which dignity he, for his moſt notorius wickedneſs, was the ſecond time depoſed, Anno. 880. By which account you ſee alſo, of how late a ſtanding he is; And how deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable in compariſon of the Authors I have cited.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
               <hi>Secondly, they object</hi> that this book is unworthy of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great. This is directly to oppoſe the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of St. <hi>Ildefonſus,</hi> St. <hi>Julian,</hi> St. <hi>Bede,</hi> and of the holy and learned Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> who thought this work worthy his tranſlation, by which alſo Greece came ſo highly to eſteem of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> as hath been ſhewed out of <hi>Baronius.</hi> This is alſo to vilifie the authority of the Latin Church, ſo much relying upon the authority of this book as hath been ſaid, and ſhall now farther be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. For you paſs on farther, and.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly object,</hi> that this book conteins many ſtories like <hi>Winter tales.</hi> I anſwer, that it is an unſufferable injury to the Church to ſay, ſhe yields ſo much credit to ſuch a book, ſo ſtuft with ſuch <hi>Winter tales,</hi> as you will have them. An unſufferable injury to our great Apoſtle St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> whom we have proved to be the writer of theſe ſtories, concerning which he himſelf ſaith in the Preface to that work. <hi>I have followed the example of St. Luke and St. Mark, who learnt the goſpell, which they write, not by ſight, but by the relation of others. Yet leaſt any in reading ſhould have an occaſion to doubt whether ſuch things as I write, be true, or no, I will ſet down by what manner, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37771:7"/> of whom I have learnt them.</hi> I know <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> (whoſe words our Adverſaries much applaud) was ſo bold as to ſay <hi>that ſome Anastarche, or Critikes, of our age would account ſome of the miracles related by him to be uncertain.</hi> But I know alſo, that the great <hi>Baronius</hi> (whoſe exactneſs in Hiſtory is famed through all Chriſtendom.) examining this cenſure of <hi>Canus</hi> (in his notes upon the Martyrologe <hi>December</hi> 23.) pronounceth it <hi>to be a calumny, very inconſiderately vented againſt a work, which both the East and West Church, for theſe thouſand years held worthy all higheſt credit, veneration, and praiſe.</hi> And then he beats down this calumny, by a multitude of moſt grave teſtimonies, <hi>I do cite thee (O</hi> Canus <hi>ſaith he) I do cite thee before the Tribunal of thy own moſt holy and moſt learned Spaniſh Doctors, S.</hi> Iſidor, S. Ildefonſus, S. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. S. Iſidor <hi>after he had enlarged himſelf in the endleſs praiſes of S.</hi> Gregory <hi>comes at laſt to conclude thus, He is happy and over happy who is well verſed in all his works. S.</hi> Ildefonſe <hi>affirmes, That all antiquity could ſhew nothing like to him</hi> (that is to the great S. <hi>Gregory) That he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed,</hi> Anthony <hi>in ſincerity,</hi> Cyprian <hi>in eloquence,</hi> Auſtin <hi>in wiſdom.</hi> Behold he preferreth this Writer of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues (which there he names with a ſpecial <hi>Encomium</hi> of that work) before the great <hi>St. Auſtin,</hi> even in point of Wiſdom: And yet theſe men dare compare him to a tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Winter tales. But <hi>Baronius</hi> goeth on and ſhewes <hi>with what reſpect theſe very Dialogues were cited by S.</hi> Julian, <hi>cited by whole Aſſemblies of Holy Fathers, (namely in</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio Triburienſi <hi>C.</hi> 17.) <hi>cited by Pope</hi> Adrian <hi>in his Epiſtle to</hi> Charles <hi>the great; cited by</hi> Jonas Aurelianenſis <hi>as moſt powerful weapons to defeat the monstrous Opinions of</hi> Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Taurinenſis; <hi>tranſlated in fine by the moſt holy Pope</hi> Zachary <hi>into Greek by reaſon of their excellency: And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account ſo much esteemed by the Greeks that they from theſe Dialogues gave the great St.</hi> Gregory <hi>the ſurname of</hi> Dialogus. <hi>Nunquid his omnibus caecutientibus tu ſolus vides? ſaith</hi> Baronius <hi>to</hi> Canus, and I ſay the ſame to any one who ſides with him in this Paradox. As for the reſt I refer my Reader to <hi>Baronius,</hi> who will eaſily ſee how
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37771:7"/> far more bitterly that moſt modeſt Cardinal would have Written againſt <hi>Canus,</hi> if he had dared to compare theſe Stories of St. <hi>Gregories</hi> to <hi>Winter tales.</hi> To us it ſufficeth, that the Church, in her Breviary, embraceth his ſtrange ſtory of the ſoul of <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> and alſo others no leſſe ſtrange in her Martyloge. <hi>Febr.</hi> 13. 15. 25. <hi>March</hi> the firſt, <hi>August</hi> the ſeventh, yea, (that which you will dread to hear) in the thirtieth one day of <hi>May,</hi> be theſe words. <hi>At Rome of St. Paſchaſius Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con and confeſſor of whom St. Gregory the Pope maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſee you not that the Church holds forth to us that very <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> for a Saint, of whom we find <hi>St. Gregory</hi> to make no other mention, but that he was in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and thence delivered by prayers? So that you ſee the Church owns that very ſtory, which, moſt of all, they would have accounted to be a Winter tale. Here then we have our Opinion of ſouls being delivered from Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory before the day of Judgment, credited by the Church. For otherwiſe ſhe could not propoſe to us a Man to be worſhipped for a Saint, of whom ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to us what is related by <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> the ſubſtance of whoſe Relation is, <hi>That being in Purgatory, be did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles That, he appeared in the bathes to beg prayers, That by theſe prayers be was releaſed,</hi> wherfore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly.</hi> they in vain object againſt this ſtory of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius,</hi> that <hi>he dyed obſtinately in Schiſm.</hi> And that it is the fancy of an idle brain to imagine that ſouls are ſent to the bathes, there to ſcrub and rub, ſo to be acquitted of their ſins. For firſt to ſay <hi>Paſchaſius dyed obstinate in Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſme,</hi> is to abuſe both St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and this Saint, and the Church, and the Reader, <hi>St. Gregory</hi> is abuſed, for in the ſame breath, in which he told his Reader how <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius</hi> was freed from Purgatory, he tells him cleerly. <hi>That ſeeing his fault proceeded not out of Malice, after death he might he purged from that ſin. And we muſt think that his plentifull almes obtained this favour, &amp;c.</hi> The Church is abuſed, which recommends to us a Man to be worſhipped for a Saint, who (as they ſay) <hi>dyed obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in Schiſme.</hi> The Saint recommended by the Church
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37771:8"/> is abuſed, whilſt they thus pluck him from Heaven, to Hell. The Reader is abuſed by ſuch groſs falſities ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded unto him, after <hi>their fuller conſideration.</hi> Far more conſiderately, that incomparable <hi>Baronius,</hi> ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe words which I now cited out of <hi>St. Gregory</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the fault of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> expounds by them theſe his other words which ſaid. <hi>That he remained in his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion untill his dying day,</hi> that is, <hi>excluſively,</hi> ſo that his Repentance happened before his death, or (which I moſt approve) that his death happened before that controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie was cleerly decided, which ſeems moſt conformable to thoſe words of <hi>St. Gregory</hi> L. 4. C. 41. ſaying that <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius whilſt he lived thought it no ſin to do what he did. Secondly,</hi> for what concerns the appearing of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> in the bathes, it is not <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> but ſome idle brain that ſpeaks of ſcrubbing and rubbing. I confeſs St. <hi>Gregory</hi> to ſpeak both here, (L. 4. C. 40.) and again C. 55. that ſuch as were in purgatory did appear ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, to ſome particular perſon, ſome inferiour kind of ſervices in the bath. God permitting this, that ſo they ſhould declare the lownes of their preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo to give them occaſion of begging the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſuch particular perſons, which could and would beſt aſſiſt them now, though <hi>Raphael</hi> the Archangel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling any regrete, performed all bumble ſervice to young <hi>Tobie,</hi> becauſe all this while he enjoyed the ſight of God, and voluntarily performed his gratious plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Yet if God, in his wrath, had caſt him from his ſight, deprived him of glory, baniſhed him from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and for his offences deputed him to thoſe inferior offices in revenge of them, it is not hard to conceive, that this had been a moſt ſad chaſticement, as it conteins the debaſing of ſo noble a nature, by the juſt wrath of his Creator againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Wherefore I wonder to hear thoſe men ſay, that no grave Divine novv living vvill undertake to juſtify theſe revelations, vvhereas <hi>Baronius</hi> hath done it ſo fully. And vvhereas they moſt carpe at this Revelation in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the very Prince of Divines, St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> doth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37771:8"/> give his approbation of alſo it in particular. For thus he Writes in Suppl. Q. 69. or 1. <hi>Moreover this is made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by what St.</hi> Gregory <hi>ſaith, L,</hi> 4. <hi>Dial. where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates that ſouls after their departure are led to ſeveral cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral places, as appears by</hi> Paſchaſius, <hi>whom</hi> Germanus <hi>the Biſhop of</hi> Capua <hi>found in the bathes.</hi> And a little after. <hi>There be allotted to ſouls after their departure certain corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places by a certain congruitie according to the degrees of their dignitie. And ſo we place ſouls, which are in a perfect participation of the Deity in heaven. But we ſay thoſe ſouls to be deputed to contrary places which are hindred from this participation.</hi> That is, We ſay they be deputed to Hell, if they be hindred from participation of Deity, by damnable ſin. Again, vve ſay they be deputed to purgatory, if they be hindred from this participation by only venial ſin. again, theſe venial ſins may be many, and great; and ſo ſink a ſoul dovvn to the bottom of of Purgatory, that is, depute that ſoul to the moſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful temporall puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nts. as alſo, they may be very fevv, and of the lighteſt kind of ſins, and thoſe alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated (in great part) by contrary great good vvorks; as they may truly think of the ſins of St. <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> ſeeing that he did miracles upon earth, vvhen his ſoul vvas ſuffering this lighter kind of puniſhment. Wherefore, though ſuch a ſoul, be deputed to a purgative ſtate; and is purged by being baniſhed from the ſight of God, yet the other penal pains be of the lighteſt ſort, ſuch as may (to our capacity) be fitly expreſſed by being out of the fiery priſon of purgatory, yet in ſome lovv, abject, dark, ſmooky place in the ground, deputed there to contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible imployments, as thoſe in the bathes were. Of vvhich the merciful indulgence of God made particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choice, that ſo thoſe ſouls might the more connaturally have commodity of begging the aſſiſtance of ſuch perſons as God ſhould connaturally diſpoſe to come thither. This is agreeable to vvhat St. <hi>Thomas</hi> novv cited, ſaith, (<hi>ad</hi> 2) <hi>That as lightſome places are commonly aſſigned to illightned ſpirits, and obſcure darkned holds to ſpirits darkned by ſins.</hi> So thoſe hot, and ſmoky, cloſe, and ſtiffling places,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37771:9"/> of the bathes, bear a convenient Metaphorical expreſſion of ſuch as are yet darkned, unvvaſhed and unpurged ſouls. It is alſo agreeable to vvhat St. <hi>Gregory</hi> there <hi>L.</hi> 4. C. 42. ſaith, diſcourſing upon this purgatory of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius.</hi> For having cited theſe vvords. <hi>Thou hast deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd me from the lower hell.</hi> He preſently adds ſo that <hi>the higher Hell</hi> (and place of lighter torments) <hi>may ſeem to be upon the earth, and the lower under the earth.</hi> Now, as it is not abſurd to expreſſe the joy of ſpirits unto us, by ſaying they did ſing merrily (as it is ſaid of the Angels in Chriſts Nativitie) though ſinging be an act as unnatural to an Angel rejoycing, as ſerving in a bath to a ſpirit purging: ſo it is not abſurd by theſe kind of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to expreſs unto us the low, and ſad eſtate of thoſe ſoules which ſhould be ſinging with Angels, if their light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſins did not baniſh them from thoſe joyes to theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bect Offices. The like is to be ſaid of that other exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple related by St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> L. 4. C. 55. To which (and the farther declaration of the former) we may fitly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what St. <hi>Thomas</hi> above cited, ſaith <hi>art.</hi> 7, <hi>ad</hi> 8. q. 69. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſeparated ſouls are ſometimes puniſhed in the place of our aboad; yet it is not becauſe that it is the proper place of puniſhment. But this done for our inſtruction, that ſeeing their pains we may be withdrawn from offending.</hi> So ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to be underſtood what is ſaid of the ſoul of <hi>Theodori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> caſt into the gulf of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> at which thoſe, who are diſpoſed, might carp as much as at his other ſtories, though it be conteined in the Breviary of the Church, yea they might as well carpe at ſome conteined in Holy writ, as that, the Devil (who is a ſpirit) ſhould be chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away from <hi>Saul</hi> by the material ſound of <hi>Davids</hi> harp. And they might ſay that it is like a <hi>Wintertale</hi> which we read <hi>Tob.</hi> 6.9. <hi>That a piece of the heart of a fiſh put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on coales, the ſmoak of it ſo chaſeth away the devil that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes no more.</hi> All this is by way of ſupererogation, ſaid in defence of this ſtorie of <hi>Paſchaſius.</hi> For though that ſhould be falſe, yet it doth not follow that thoſe Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues were not vvritten by St. <hi>Gregorie.</hi> And ſtill it doth follovv that St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> thought it to be true, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37771:9"/> he judged it to be a truth confirmed by Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That ſouls are deliverable from purgatory before the day of judgment, and the Church judged the ſame, vvhilſt ſhe in her Martirologe credited vvhat Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie mentions of Paſchaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
               <hi>Fifthly and laſtly,</hi> they object that nothing like ſuch Winter tales, can be found in the other worthy works of St. <hi>Gregorie.</hi> A ſtrange objection to proceed from a Scholler, upon his <hi>further conſideration.</hi> For the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of any mean Scholler might have made him reflect, how often <hi>St. Gregorie,</hi> in this very <hi>fourth book of his Dialogues</hi> (out of which only they have gleened the few ſtories, at which they take ſo great exceptions) doth relate the very ſelf ſame ſtories, which, he himſelf tels you, he had formerly related in his Homilies. His Homilies be ſo eſteemed by the Church, that ſhe hath transferred more out of them into her Breviary, then out of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Father. Yet how thick be theſe his Homilies ſtored with theſe ſtories.</p>
            <p>L. 4. C. 14. <hi>I remember</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that, in my Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies upon the goſpel, I told a ſtorie of Servulus,</hi> which here he repeats out of Hom. 15.</p>
            <p>Again C. 15. <hi>in the ſame Homilies, I remember likewiſe how I told a certain thing of Redempta and Romula..</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again C. 16. <hi>I will here report this, which I remember alſo to have ſpoke of in my Homilies concerning my Aunt</hi> Tarſilla. <hi>To this Woman</hi> Felix <hi>my Grandfather ſometime Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>Hom.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p>Again C. 19. <hi>By the relation of the ſame</hi> Probus, <hi>and other religious men, I came to the Relation of ſuch things, as in my Homilies I told to my Auditors, concerning the Venerable Father</hi> Steven.</p>
            <p>Again C. 27. <hi>Concerning the Earle</hi> Theophanius, <hi>I did in my Homilies make publick mention of ſuch ſtrange things as happened to him, Hom.</hi> 36. <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again <hi>C.</hi> 37. <hi>There was one</hi> Theodorus <hi>(which story I remember in my Homilies to the people, I have ſpoke of alſo) who was a very unruly lad, &amp;c. Hom.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>Again, he word for word C. 38. Relates that dreadfull
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37771:10"/> ſtory concerning <hi>Criſaptius</hi> juſt as he had related it, Hom. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Now Note I pray, that theſe two laſt cited chapters have but one chapter between them and the chapter which conteines the ſtory of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> at which they take ſo great exceptions. And yet theſe conſiderate writers neither marked what was ſaid ſo often, either in the ſame fourth book, or in theſe two ſo neer bordering chapters, but boldly deny that St. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his other works hath no ſuch ſtories, as occurr every wherein his Dialogues.</p>
            <p>Though I need not ſeek further to refute this apparent falſity then what hath been already cited out of his Homilies, yet I cannot but tell you that you ſhall find ſome of his Epiſtles alſo moſt plentifully ſtored with divers ſuch ſtories, as they are pleaſed to compare to Winter-tales. L. 3. <hi>Regiſter Indict.</hi> 12. Ep. 30. And L. 9. <hi>Regiſter Indict.</hi> 4. <hi>Epist.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> I do not here anſwer a weak cavel, which I find them to uſe, ſo to diſcredit that moſt credible ſtory, which St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> relates of a Monk in his own Monaſtery, whoſe ſoul was freed from Purgatory, after he had appointed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for forty dayes together to be offered for his ſoul: for when I ſhall bring this ſtory in proof of our opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſhall demonſtrate that cavell to be wholly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ignorance of antiquity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> I will end by giving my Reader an account out of what ſhop all this falſe wares have been fetcht. The Enemies of the Roman Church ſeeing ſuch a multitude of ſtories, related by the great St. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to their novelties, have deviſed all the ſhifts they can, to cry down the Authority of his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus, as you may ſee in <hi>Criticis ſacris Riveti Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 29. Where he cites the very place of <hi>Canus</hi> ſo much magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by our adverſaries, to diſparadge theſe dialogues. But <hi>Rivetus</hi> could alledge no one more ancient then <hi>Clemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> who reliſhed not this work, though he found ſome who imagined Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> not the third but the ſecond of that name, to have been the Author of theſe Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, which we have demonſtratively (as I dare ſay)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37771:10"/> ſhewed to be moſt falſe. And whereas <hi>Chemnitius</hi> ſaith, that neither the ſtile, nor the contents of this book ſute well with the other works of St. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> we have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the falſity of both, by the Authorities cited out of his Homilies, againſt which work <hi>Rivetus</hi> hath not a word to <hi>ſay,</hi> but moſt ignorantly carps at <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Fronto Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus,</hi> for eſteeming the great St. <hi>Gregorie</hi> to have been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dialogus</hi> by the Greeks; for if it be true which he ſaith of <hi>Cedrenus,</hi> that the occaſion of this ſurname pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the Book of Dialogues written by this <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius,</hi> then this <hi>Gregorie</hi> muſt needs be the perſon who did write theſe Dialogues: but the perſon who did write theſe Dialogues could neither be <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Second or the Third, as hath been demonſtrated, but evidently is <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt, whom we uſually call <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great; whence it remains moſt cleerly convinced, that the Great St. <hi>Gregory</hi> is the Man who by occaſion of his Dialogues was by the Grecians ſurnamed <hi>Dialogus,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Author of theſe Dialogues we ſpeak of.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
